Williams Obstetrics.
Chapter 13: Gestational Trophoblastic Disease.
Hydatidiform Mole—Molar Pregnancy Pathogenesis Diagnosis Management Gestational Trophoblastic Neoplasia Diagnosis, Staging, And Prognostic Scoring Treatment Subsequent Pregnancy References Gestational trophoblastic disease (GTD) is the term used to encompass a group of tumors typified by abnormal trophoblast proliferation.
Trophoblast produces human chorionic gonadotropin (hCG).
Thus, the measurement of this peptide hormone in serum is essential for GTD diagnosis, management, and surveillance.
GTD histologically is divided into hydatidiform moles, which are characterized by the presence of villi, and nonmolar trophoblastic malignant neoplasms, which lack villi.
Hydatidiform moles are excessively edematous immature placentas .
These include the benign complete hydatidiform mole and partial hydatidiform mole .
The third member is the malignant invasive mole .
Invasive mole is deemed malignant because of its marked penetration into and destruction of the myometrium and its ability to metastasize.
Table 13-1.
Modified WHO Classification of GTD Nonmolar trophoblastic neoplasms include choriocarcinoma, placental site trophoblastic tumor, and epithelioid trophoblastic tumor .
These three are differentiated by the trophoblast type that they contain.
Under the GTD umbrella term, the malignant forms of GTD are termed gestational trophoblastic neoplasia (GTN).
These include invasive mole, choriocarcinoma, placental site trophoblastic tumor, and epithelioid trophoblastic tumor.
These malignancies develop weeks or years following any type of pregnancy, but more frequently follow hydatidiform mole.
Each GTN malignancy type is histologically distinct and varies in its propensity to invade and metastasize.
However, these diagnoses are infrequently identified from an actual histological specimen.
Instead, measurement of serum hCG levels and clinical findings are more often used to diagnose and treat this malignancy.
Accordingly, GTN is often managed as a single composite clinical entity.
With chemotherapy, most tumors currently are highly curable.
Hydatidiform Mole.
Classic histological findings of molar pregnancy include trophoblast proliferation and villi with stromal edema .
The degree of histological changes, karyotype and immunostaining differences, and the absence or presence of embryonic elements are used to classify them as either complete or partial hydatidiform moles .
These two also vary in their associated risks for developing medical comorbidities and postevacuation GTN.
Of the two, GTN more frequently follows complete hydatidiform mole.
Figure 13-1.
Complete hydatidiform mole.
A. Gross specimen with characteristic vesicles of variable size.
Photograph contributed by Dr. Sasha Andrews.
Reproduced with permission from Patel S, Roberts S, Rogers V, et al [eds]: Williams Obstetrics Study Guide, 25th ed.
New York, NY: McGraw Hill; 2019.
B. Low-magnification photomicrograph shows generalized edema and cistern formation (black asterisks) within avascular villi.
Haphazard trophoblastic hyperplasia is marked by a yellow asterisk on the right.
Reproduced with permission from Dr. Erika Fong.
Table 13-2.
Features of Partial and Complete Hydatidiform Moles Grossly, complete moles have abnormal chorionic villi that appear as a mass of clear vesicles.
These vary in size and often hang in clusters from thin pedicles.
In contrast, partial molar pregnancies have focal and less advanced hydatidiform changes and contain some fetal tissue.
Both forms of moles usually fill the uterine cavity, but they rarely may be ectopic (Sebire, 2005; Yamada, 2016).
# Epidemiology and Risk Factors.
Ethnic predisposition is seen with hydatidiform mole, and prevalences are higher in Asians, Hispanics, and American Indians (Choi, 2015; Drake, 2006).
The incidence in the United States and Europe has been relatively constant at 1 per 1000 deliveries (Eysbouts, 2016; Melamed, 2016).
The strongest risk factors are age and a prior hydatidiform mole.
Women at both extremes of reproductive age
are most vulnerable (Savage, 2013; Sebire, 2002a).
With a prior complete mole, the risk of another mole is 0.9 percent, and with a previous partial mole, the rate is 0.3 percent.
After two prior complete moles, approximately 20 percent of women have a third mole .
# Pathogenesis.
Molar pregnancies typically arise from chromosomally abnormal fertilizations.
Complete moles most often have a diploid chromosomal composition.
These usually are 46,XX and result from androgenesis, meaning both sets of chromosomes are paternal.
The chromosomes of the ovum are either absent or inactivated.
As shown in Figure 13-2A, an ovum is fertilized by a haploid sperm, which then duplicates its own chromosomes after meiosis.
Less commonly, the chromosomal pattern may be 46,XY or 46,XX and due to fertilization by two sperm, that is, dispermic fertilization or dispermy (Lawler, 1991; Ohama, 1981).
Figure 13-2.
Typical pathogenesis of complete and partial moles.
A. A 46,XX complete mole may be formed if a 23,X-bearing haploid sperm penetrates a 23,X-containing haploid egg whose genes have been “inactivated.
Paternal chromosomes then duplicate to create a 46,XX diploid complement solely of paternal origin.
B. A partial mole may be formed if two sperm—either 23,X- or 23,Y-bearing—both fertilize (dispermy) a 23,X-containing haploid egg whose genes have not been inactivated.
The resulting fertilized egg is triploid with two chromosome sets being donated by the father (diandry).
Partial moles have a triploid karyotype, which is 69,XXX, 69,XXY, or much less commonly, 69,XYY.
These are each composed of two paternal haploid sets of chromosomes contributed by dispermy and one maternal haploid set (see Fig. 13-2B).
Less frequently, a similar haploid egg may be fertilized by an unreduced diploid 46,XY sperm.
These triploid zygotes result in some embryonic development, however, it ultimately is a lethal fetal condition (Joergensen, 2014; Lakovschek, 2011).
Fetuses that reach advanced ages have severe growth restriction, multiple congenital anomalies, or both.
Twin Pregnancy Rarely, in some twin pregnancies, one chromosomally normal fetus is paired with a complete diploid molar pregnancy.
Importantly, these cases must be distinguished from a single partial molar pregnancy with its associated abnormal fetus.
Other potential diagnoses include placental mesenchymal dysplasia, subchorionic hematoma, or chorioangioma .
To help distinguish among these, chorionic villus sampling, amniocentesis, or fetal cord blood sampling coupled with fetal karyotyping aid confirmation .
Several unique pregnancy problems complicate such twin pregnancies.
Thyrotoxicosis is common, but the most worrisome are preeclampsia or hemorrhage.
These frequently necessitate preterm delivery.
Thus, many women may choose to terminate the gestation, if diagnosed early.
In those with continuing pregnancy, survival of the normal fetus varies and depends on associated comorbidity from the molar component.
Wee and Jauniaux (2005) reviewed outcomes in 174 women, of whom 82 chose termination.
Of the remaining 92 pregnancies, 42 percent either miscarried or had a perinatal death; approximately 60 percent delivered preterm; and 40 percent delivered at term.
Another concern for those continuing their pregnancy is the risk for developing subsequent GTN.
Most evidence indicates no significant difference between women who continue or terminate their pregnancy (Lin, 2017; Sebire 2002b).
# Clinical Findings.
Molar pregnancy is diagnosed sooner than in the past because prenatal care is sought much earlier and sonography is virtually universal.
For example, in 194 women with a complete mole, evacuation was completed at a median gestational age of 9 weeks and at 12 weeks for 172 patients with a partial mole .
As a result, most molar pregnancies are treated before complications ensue.
Typically, 1 to 2 months of amenorrhea precede the diagnosis.
As gestation advances, symptoms tend to be more pronounced with complete compared with partial moles .
Untreated molar pregnancies will almost always cause
uterine bleeding that varies from spotting to profuse hemorrhage.
Bleeding may presage spontaneous molar abortion, but more often, it follows an intermittent course for weeks to months.
In more advanced moles with considerable concealed uterine hemorrhage, moderate iron-deficiency anemia develops.
Nausea and vomiting also may be significant.
Of physical findings, many women have uterine growth exceeding that expected, and the enlarged uterus is comparatively softer.
Fetal heart motion is absent with complete moles.
The ovaries can be fuller and cystic from multiple theca-lutein cysts .
These are more common with a complete mole and likely result from ovarian overstimulation by excessive hCG levels.
Remember that hCG and luteinizing hormone share the same receptor, and both can stimulate the theca layer that surrounds follicles.
Because theca-lutein cysts regress following pregnancy evacuation and subsequent hCG level decline, expectant management is preferred.
Occasionally, a larger cyst may undergo torsion, infarction, and hemorrhage.
However, oophorectomy is not performed unless extensive infarction persists after untwisting.
Figure 13-3.
Sonogram of an ovary with multiple theca-lutein cysts in a woman with a complete hydatidiform mole.
The thyrotropin-like effects of hCG frequently cause serum free thyroxine (fT4) levels to be elevated and thyroid-stimulating hormone (TSH) levels to be decreased .
Despite this, clinically apparent thyrotoxicosis is unusual and in our experience can be mimicked by bleeding and sepsis from infected products.
Moreover, the serum free T4 levels rapidly normalize after uterine evacuation.
Despite this, cases of presumed “thyroid storm” have been reported .
Severe preeclampsia and eclampsia are relatively common with advanced molar pregnancies.
However, these are seldom seen today because of early diagnosis and evacuation.
An exception is the case of a normal fetus coexisting with a complete mole, described earlier.
In continuing twin gestations, severe preeclampsia frequently mandates preterm delivery.
# Diagnosis.
Serum β-HCG Measurements Most women initially have irregular bleeding that almost always prompts pregnancy testing and sonography.
Less often, women will spontaneously pass molar tissue.
With a complete molar pregnancy, serum β-hCG levels are commonly elevated above those expected for gestational age.
With more advanced moles, values in the millions are not unusual.
Importantly, these high values can lead to erroneous false-negative urine pregnancy test results.
Termed a hook effect, excessive β-hCG hormone levels oversaturate the assay’s targeting antibody and create a false-negative reading .
In these cases, serum β-hCG determinations with or without sample dilution will yield a positive result.
With a partial mole, β-hCG levels may also be significantly elevated, but more commonly concentrations are in ranges expected for gestational age.
Sonography Although this is the mainstay of trophoblastic disease diagnosis, not all cases are confirmed initially.
In a large series of more than 1000 patients with molar pregnancy, sonography’s sensitivity was 44 percent, and its specificity was 74 percent .
With grayscale sonography, a complete mole appears as an echogenic uterine mass filling the endometrial cavity and is surrounded by normal myometrium.
The mass is composed of numerous anechoic cystic spaces of different sizes and shapes, but without a fetus or amnionic sac.
The appearance is often described as a “snowstorm” .
Application of color Doppler displays marked surrounding myometrial vascularity.
However, absent internal flow reflects the avascular villi of complete moles.
Figure 13-4.
Sonograms of hydatidiform moles.
A. Transverse view of a uterus with a complete hydatidiform mole.
The characteristic “snowstorm” appearance reflects an echogenic uterine mass, marked by calipers, that has numerous anechoic cystic spaces.
Notably, a fetus or amnionic sac is absent.
B. In this sagittal image of a partial hydatidiform mole, the fetal head (arrow) lies
adjacent to an enlarged, multicystic placenta.
A partial mole has features that include a thick, multicystic placenta plus a fetus or fetal tissue.
Thin septa can be found within the gestational sac .
Affected fetuses usually die in the first trimester.
Those advancing further often show growth restriction, oligohydramnios, and limb or CNS defects .
In early pregnancy, however, these sonographic characteristics are seen in fewer than half of hydatidiform moles.
At earlier gestations, a complete mole may appear as a polypoid hyperechoic mass that lacks internal cysts and is surrounded by anechoic fluid .
The most common mimics are incomplete or missed abortion.
In these cases, histological evaluation, described next, ultimately is diagnostic.
Occasionally, molar pregnancy may be confused for a multifetal pregnancy or a uterine leiomyoma with cystic degeneration.
Pathology Because of the risk for subsequent GTN following molar pregnancy, postevacuation surveillance is indicated.
Thus, moles must be distinguished from other pregnancy types that are not molar but that have hydropic placental degeneration.
Most often, these are hydropic abortuses formed by the traditional union of one haploid egg and one haploid sperm but are pregnancies that have failed.
Their placentas display hydropic degeneration, in which villi are edematous and swollen, and thus mimic some villous features of hydatidiform moles.
These mimics do not require postevacuation surveillance.
Some distinguishing histological characteristics are shown in Table 13-2.
In pregnancies before 10 weeks, classic molar histological changes may not be apparent.
Villi may not be enlarged, and molar stroma may not yet be edematous and avascular.
Histopathologic evaluation can be enhanced by immunohistochemical staining for p57 expression and by molecular genotyping .
p57KIP2 is a nuclear protein whose gene is paternally imprinted and maternally expressed.
This means that the gene product is produced only in tissues containing a maternal allele.
Because complete moles contain only paternal genes, the p57KIP2 protein is absent in complete moles, and tissues do not pick up this stain .
In contrast, this nuclear protein is strongly expressed in normal placentas, in spontaneous pregnancy losses with hydropic degeneration, and in partial hydatidiform moles .
Accordingly, immunostaining for p57KIP2 is an effective means to isolate complete mole from the diagnostic list.
For distinction of a partial mole from a nonmolar hydropic abortus, both of which express p57KIP2, molecular genotyping can be used .
Molecular genotyping determines the parental source of alleles.
Thereby, it can distinguish among a diploid diandric genome (complete mole), a triploid diandric-monogynic genome (partial mole), or biparental diploidy (nonmolar abortus) .
# Management.
Maternal deaths from molar pregnancies are rare because of early diagnosis, timely evacuation, and vigilant postevacuation surveillance for GTN .
Preoperative evaluation strives to identify potential complications, such as preeclampsia, hyperthyroidism, anemia, electrolyte depletions from hyperemesis, and metastatic disease .
Most recommend chest radiography, whereas computed tomography (CT) and magnetic resonance (MR) imaging are not routinely done unless a chest radiograph shows lung lesions or unless other extrauterine disease is suspected.
Table 13-3.
Some Considerations for Management of Hydatidiform Mole Molar Pregnancy Termination Regardless of uterine size, molar evacuation by suction curettage usually is the preferred treatment.
Preoperative cervical dilation with an osmotic dilator is recommended if the cervix is minimally dilated.
Intraoperative bleeding can be greater with molar pregnancy than with a comparably sized uterus containing nonmolar products.
Thus with large moles, adequate anesthesia, sufficient intravenous access, and blood-banking support is imperative.
A step by step description of dilation and curettage is found in Chapter 11 (p. 213).
For molar evacuation, the cervix is mechanically dilated to preferably
allow insertion of a large Karman suction cannula.
Depending on uterine size, a 10- to 14-mm diameter is typical.
As evacuation is begun, oxytocin is infused to limit bleeding.
Intraoperative sonography is often recommended to help ensure complete uterine cavity emptying and minimize perforation risk.
When the myometrium has contracted, a thorough but gentle curettage with a sharp large-loop Sims curette may be performed.
If bleeding continues despite uterine evacuation and oxytocin infusion, other uterotonic agents are given .
Uncommonly, pelvic arterial embolization, uterine packing, or hysterectomy may be necessary .
Some volume of trophoblast is deported into the pelvic venous system during molar evacuation .
With large moles, the amount of tissue may be sufficient to produce clinically apparent respiratory insufficiency, pulmonary edema, or even embolism .
In our earlier experiences with substantial moles, these and their chest radiographic manifestations clear rapidly without specific treatment.
Following curettage, anti-D immunoglobulin (Rhogam) is given to Rh Dnegative women because fetal tissues with a partial mole may include red cells with D-antigen .
Those with suspected complete mole are similarly treated because a definitive diagnosis of complete versus partial mole may not be confirmed until histological evaluation of the evacuated products.
Following evacuation, the long-term prognosis for women with a hydatidiform mole is not improved with prophylactic chemotherapy.
Moreover, chemotherapy toxicity can be significant, and thus it is not recommended routinely (Gueye, 2014; Wang, 2017).
Methods other than suction curettage can be considered for select cases.
Hysterectomy with ovarian preservation may be preferable for women who have finished childbearing and who carry complete moles with high-risk features.
Of women aged 40 to 49 years, up to 50 percent will subsequently develop GTN, and hysterectomy markedly reduces this likelihood (Elias, 2012; Zhao, 2019).
During hysterectomy, theca-lutein cysts do not require removal, and they spontaneously regress following molar termination.
Last, labor induction or hysterotomy is seldom used for molar evacuation in the United States.
Both will likely increase blood loss and theoretically may raise the incidence of persistent trophoblastic disease .
Postevacuation Surveillance Close biochemical surveillance for persistent gestational neoplasia follows each hydatidiform mole evacuation.
Serial measurement of serum β-hCG levels aim to detect persistent or renewed trophoblastic proliferation.
As a glycoprotein, hCG shows structural heterogeneity and exists in different isoforms.
Thus, for surveillance, an hCG assay that can detect all forms of hCG should be used (Harvey, 2010; Ngan, 2018).
These are different from those used for routine pregnancy testing (de Medeiros, 2009).
The initial βhCG level is obtained within 48 hours after evacuation.
This serves as the baseline, which is compared with β-hCG quantification done thereafter every 1 to 2 weeks.
Levels are followed until they become undetectable.
The median time for such resolution is 6 weeks for partial moles and 7 weeks for complete moles.
Of patients, 95 percent have normal β-hCG levels by 14 weeks postevacuation and 99 percent by 25 weeks .
Once β-hCG is undetectable, this is confirmed with monthly determinations for another 6 months (Lurain, 2010; Sebire, 2007).
Concurrently, reliable contraception is imperative to avoid confusion caused by rising β-hCG levels from a new pregnancy.
Most recommend combination hormonal contraception, injectable depot medroxyprogesterone acetate, or progestin implant.
The latter two are particularly useful if poor patient compliance is anticipated.
Intrauterine devices are not used until βhCG levels are undetectable because of the risk of uterine perforation if an invasive mole is present.
After these 6 months, monitoring is discontinued and pregnancy allowed.
Although not recommended, if a woman conceives during surveillance, live-birth and congenital anomalies rates
appear to mirror general population rates .
During β-hCG levels surveillance, increasing or persistently plateaued levels mandate evaluation for GTN.
If the woman has not become pregnant, these levels signify trophoblast proliferation that is most likely malignant.
Several factors predispose a patient to GTN following molar evacuation.
Complete moles have a 15 to 20 percent incidence of malignant sequelae, compared with 1 to 5 percent following partial moles.
Surprisingly, with much earlier recognition and evacuation of molar pregnancies, the risk for GTN has not dropped .
Other GTN risk factors are older maternal age, preevacuation β-hCG levels >100,000 mIU/mL, uterine size that is large-for-gestational age, theca-lutein cysts >6 cm, and a slow decline in β-hCG levels (Berkowitz, 2009; Kang, 2012; Wolfberg, 2005).
Gestational Trophoblastic Neoplasia.
This group includes invasive mole, choriocarcinoma, placental site trophoblastic tumor, and epithelioid trophoblastic tumor.
These tumors almost always develop with or after some form of recognized pregnancy.
Half follow hydatidiform mole, a fourth follow miscarriage or tubal pregnancy, and another fourth develop after a preterm or term pregnancy .
These four tumor types are histologically distinct but are usually diagnosed solely by persistently elevated serum β-hCG levels because tissue is infrequently available for study.
Criteria to diagnose postmolar GTN are shown in Table 13-4.
Table 13-4.
Criteria for Diagnosis of Gestational Trophoblastic Neoplasia # Diagnosis, Staging, and Prognostic Scoring.
Clinically, these placental tumors are characterized by their aggressive invasion into the myometrium and propensity to metastasize.
The most common finding with GTN is irregular bleeding associated with uterine subinvolution.
The bleeding may be continuous or intermittent and sometimes may be sudden and massive.
Myometrial perforation from trophoblastic growth can cause intraperitoneal hemorrhage.
In some women, lower genital tract metastases are evident.
In others, only distant metastases, with no trace of uterine tumor, are found.
Consideration for the possibility of GTN is the most important factor in its recognition.
Unusually persistent bleeding after any type of pregnancy should prompt serum β-hCG level measurement.
Uterine size is assessed, and careful examination seeks lower genital tract metastases, which usually are bluish vascular masses .
Tissue biopsy of such masses is unnecessary and may cause significant bleeding.
Once the diagnosis is verified, a baseline serum β-hCG level and hemogram are obtained.
A search for local disease and metastases includes tests of liver and renal function, transvaginal sonography, chest CT or radiography, and brain and abdominopelvic CT scan or MR imaging.
Less often, positron-emission tomographic (PET) scanning and cerebrospinal fluid β-hCG level determination are used to identify metastases .
If no extrauterine disease is found, a second curettage or hysterectomy may be considered.
After either, β-hCG levels are then measured every 2 weeks until three consecutively lie in undetectable range.
Levels are subsequently repeated monthly for 6 months.
In contrast, if β-hCG levels persist after curettage or hysterectomy or if initial extrauterine disease is found, patients undergo staging and chemotherapy is instituted (Koh, 2018; Osborne, 2016).
GTN is staged clinically using the system of the International Federation of Gynecology and Obstetrics (FIGO) (2009).
This includes a modification of the World Health Organization (WHO) (1983) prognostic index score, with which scores of 0 to 4 are given for each of the categories shown in Table 13-5.
Women with WHO scores of 0 to 6 are considered to have lowrisk disease, whereas those with scores ≥7 are considered in the high-risk group.
TABLE 13-5.
International Federation of Gynecology and Obstetrics (FIGO) Staging and Diagnostic Scoring System for Gestational Trophoblastic Neoplasia # Histological Classification.
Clinical staging is assigned without regard to histological
findings, even if available.
Still, distinct histological types are recognized.
Invasive Mole These are a common trophoblastic neoplasm, and almost all invasive moles arise from partial or complete moles.
Previously known as chorioadenoma destruens, invasive mole is characterized by extensive tissue invasion by trophoblast and whole villi.
Trophoblastic cells penetrate deep into the myometrium and sometimes involve the peritoneum, adjacent parametrium, or vaginal vault.
Although locally aggressive, invasive moles are less prone to metastasize.
Gestational Choriocarcinoma This is the most common trophoblastic neoplasm to follow a term pregnancy or a miscarriage, and only a fourth of cases follow a molar gestation .
Choriocarcinoma is composed of cells reminiscent of early cytotrophoblast and syncytiotrophoblast, however, it contains no villi.
This rapidly growing tumor invades both myometrium and blood vessels to create hemorrhage and necrosis.
Myometrial tumor may spread outward and become visible on the uterine surface as dark, irregular nodules.
Metastases often develop early and are generally blood-borne.
The most common sites are the lungs and vagina, but tumor may travel to the vulva, kidneys, liver, brain, ovaries, and bowel.
With choriocarcinomas, ovarian theca-lutein cysts commonly coexist.
Placental Site Trophoblastic Tumor This uncommon tumor arises from intermediate trophoblasts at the placental site.
These tumors have associated serum β-hCG levels that may be only modestly elevated .
However, they produce variant forms of hCG, and identifying a high proportion of free β-hCG favors this diagnosis .
Treatment of placental site trophoblastic tumor by hysterectomy is preferred because these locally invasive tumors are usually resistant to chemotherapy.
For higher-risk stage I and for later stages, adjuvant multidrug chemotherapy also is given (Koh, 2018; Schmid, 2009).
Epithelioid Trophoblastic Tumor This rare tumor develops from chorionic-type intermediate trophoblast.
The uterus is mainly involved, and bleeding but low hCG levels are typical findings .
Primary treatment is hysterectomy because this tumor is relatively resistant to chemotherapy.
Metastatic disease is common, and combination chemotherapy is employed (Frijstein, 2019; Koh, 2018).
# Treatment.
Women with GTN are best managed by oncologists, and some evidence supports treatment in centers specializing in GTN .
Chemotherapy alone is usually the primary treatment.
In some GTN cases without extrauterine disease, a second uterine evacuation may be an adjuvant therapeutic option to avoid or minimize chemotherapy (Hemida, 2019; Koh, 2018; Pezeshki, 2004).
In other cases, suction curettage may infrequently be needed to resolve bleeding or remove a substantial amount of retained molar tissue.
In specific cases, hysterectomy may be primary or adjuvant treatment (Bolze, 2018; Eysbouts, 2017b).
Single-agent chemotherapy protocols are usually sufficient for nonmetastatic or low-risk metastatic neoplasia (Lawrie, 2016; Koh, 2018).
In their review of 108 women with low-risk disease, Abrão and colleagues (2008) reported that monotherapy protocols with either methotrexate or actinomycin D were equally effective compared with a regimen containing both.
In general, methotrexate is less toxic than actinomycin D (Chan, 2006; Seckl, 2010).
Regimens are repeated until serum β-hCG levels are undetectable.
Combination chemotherapy is given for high-risk disease, and reported cure rates approximate 90 percent .
Several regimens are successful.
One is EMA-CO, which includes etoposide, methotrexate, actinomycin D, cyclophosphamide, and vincristine (Oncovin).
In selected cases, adjuvant surgical and radiotherapy also may be employed .
Despite chemotherapy successes in general, frequent causes of death include hemorrhage from metastatic sites, respiratory failure, sepsis, and multiorgan failure due to widespread chemoresistant disease (Lybol, 2012; Neubauer, 2015).
With either low- or high-risk disease, once serum β-hCG levels are undetectable, serosurveillance is
continued for 1 year.
During this time, effective contraception is crucial to avoid teratogenic effects of chemotherapy to the fetus and to mitigate confusion from rising β-hCG levels caused by superimposed pregnancy.
A few women during surveillance, despite no evidence of metastases, will be found to have very low β-hCG levels that plateau.
This phenomenon is called quiescent hCG and presumably stems from dormant trophoblast.
Close observation without therapy is recommended, but 20 percent will eventually have recurrent active and progressive GTN .
Subsequent Pregnancy.
Women with prior hydatidiform mole generally do not have impaired fertility, and their pregnancy outcomes are usually normal (Joneborg, 2014; Matsui, 2001; Sebire, 2003).
One concern is the 1-percent risk for developing trophoblastic disease in a subsequent pregnancy (p. 237).
Sonographic evaluation is recommended in early pregnancy, and subsequently as needed.
Women with GTN who have successfully completed chemotherapy are advised to delay pregnancy for 1 year.
Most relapses develop within this time period .
Also, methotrexate may persist in human tissues for months .
Despite this, women who become pregnant within 1 year postchemotherapy for GTN can be reassured of a likely favorable outcome .
Risk of miscarriage or GTN relapse is not increased compared with women conceiving after the suggested 1-year surveillance .
However, these gravidas are advised that the diagnosis of a tumor relapse may be delayed during pregnancy (Blagden, 2002; Tuncer, 1999a).
In general, fertility and pregnancy outcomes following GTN treatment are typically normal, and congenital anomaly rates are not increased (Berkowitz, 2000; Tse, 2012).
One exception is a higher stillbirth rate of 1.5 percent compared with a background rate of 0.8 percent .
For those with prior hydatidiform mole or GTN treatment, the placenta or products of conception in a subsequent pregnancy are sent for pathological evaluation at delivery.
A serum β-hCG level also is measured 6 weeks postpartum (Lurain, 2010; Royal College of Obstetricians and Gynaecologists, 2010).
This assay may be less valuable for those solely with a prior mole compared with those previously treated for GTN .